<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the garrison of London-Derry, in the extremity of the siege Wherein is briefly and truly represented, the deplorable miseries and calamities which they endur'd before the arrival of Maj. Gen. Kirk. By the reverend Mr. Seth Whittle, late rector of Balliachy, in the county of London-derry. Licens'd, James Fraser.</title>
            <author>Whittle, Seth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832368</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832368</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36841</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36841)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2103:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the garrison of London-Derry, in the extremity of the siege Wherein is briefly and truly represented, the deplorable miseries and calamities which they endur'd before the arrival of Maj. Gen. Kirk. By the reverend Mr. Seth Whittle, late rector of Balliachy, in the county of London-derry. Licens'd, James Fraser.</title>
                  <author>Whittle, Seth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>re-printed in the year, 1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy scorched along outer margin, with loss of text; print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36841:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the GARRISON OF London-Derry, IN THE Extremity of the SIEGE.</p>
            <p>Wherein is briefly and truly repreſented, The Deplorable Miſeries &amp; Calamities which they endur'd before the Arrival of Maj. Gen. KIRK.</p>
            <p>By the Reverend Mr. <hi>SETH WHITTLE,</hi> late Rector of <hi>Balliachy,</hi> in the County of <hi>London-derry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenc'd,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>James Fraſer.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Re. Printed in the Year, 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36841:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:36841:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:36841:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36841:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <head>A Sermon Preached before the Garriſon of <hi>LONDON-DERRY,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. I. Verſ. xviii, xix.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>For behold, I have made thee this day a defenced City, and an Iron Pillar, and Brazen Walls againſt the whole Land, againſt the Kings of Judah, againſt the Princes thereof, againſt the Prieſts thereof, and against the People of the Land.</p>
                  <p>And they ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not prevail against thee: For I am with thee, ſaith the Lord, to deliver thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved Brethren, Fellow-Actors, and Fellow-Sufferers.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Holy Scriptures are ſo univerſally reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and comprehenſive, ſo adapted to all the Neceſſities and Occaſions of Mankind, that whatſoever his Station, Calling or Imployment be, or whatſoever Temptation he may ly under; he ſhall there meet with Caution, Inſtruction and Direction, pertinent and ſufficient to guide him in all the Intricacies of Worldly Accidents, and humane Tranſactions. From this Fountain do ſpring Cordial-waters for the fainting Souls, healing for the wounded Spirits, purging for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous and peccant Humors. In them we meet with Documents to Teach us; Precepts to awe us; Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to admoniſh us; Promiſes to encourage us; and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to lead us. We are humbled by them in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and revived in Adverſity. When the Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Enemies are arrived at the utmoſt pitch of Malice; When we are neglected by our Friends, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by our Foes, reduced to the utmoſt Extremities,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36841:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->which are the uſual Concomitants of War, and Famine; when we are deprived of all viſible appearances of ſafety, and all probable means of eſcape; He that watcheth over us, and without whoſe ſuperintendency the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man waketh but in vain, deſcends to viſit us, to Relieve us in the Extremity of our Diſtreſs, Refreſhing us with this comfortable Aſſurance. <hi>For behold I have made Thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Text divideth it ſelf eaſily into three Parts. Firſt, a Gracious Declaration of the Mercy and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God to his People, in theſe Words; <hi>For behold, I have made Thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A firm Aſſurance of Protection, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, in theſe Words: <hi>And they ſhall fight againſt Thee, but ſhall not prevail againſt Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, An infallible Reaſon to fortifie their Hopes: <hi>For I am with Thee, ſaith the Lord, to deliver Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt may be ſubdivided into theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Firſt, a relative Word, <hi>For.</hi> Secondly, a Word of Attention, <hi>Behold.</hi> Thirdly, a Narration of what is done, <hi>They are made a defenced City, an iron Pillar, and brazen Wall.</hi> Fourthly, the Author and Original of this Strength, <hi>I have made Thee.</hi> Fifthly, the Adverſaries againſt whom this Strength and Defence is made; <hi>The whole Land, the Kings of Judah, the Princes, and the Prieſts.</hi> Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Time when, <hi>This Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond conſiſts, firſt of a Denunciation, or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, <hi>They ſhall fight againſt Thee.</hi> Secondly, a Prediction, or Incou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agement, <hi>They ſhall not prevail againſt Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> third contains a Notice given of the Preſence and Aſſiſtance of God, <hi>I am with thee;</hi> Secondly, the Effect and Operation of his Preſence, <hi>To deliver thee;</hi> Thirdly, the Reaſon and Cauſe, why they may expect Deliverance, <hi>ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36841:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
The word, <hi>For,</hi> hath a Relation to the antecedent verſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Chapter, where the Prophet enumerats the Actions and Practices of the People of the North, That <hi>they ſha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> come and ſet every man his Throne at the entring of the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and againſt the Walls thereof, yet the City ſhall be delivered, the enemies of the North ſhall not prevail against it, for it is made a defenced City, an Iron Pillar, and Brazen Walls,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The word, <hi>Behold,</hi> commands an attention; <hi>Look to it, and obſerve it, it is the Lord hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall ſurely come to paſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time when, ought to be regarded with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Joy, and Satisfaction; there ſhall be no delatory Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, nor obſtruction in their Deliverance and Safety, they ſhall ſuddenly eſcape, for it is done, <hi>This Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Princes of the Land, confederating with the Prieſts, and followed by the People, ſhall beſiege <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> caſt up Trenches about it, aſſault the Walls, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all the Miſchiefs, that Rage &amp; Malice can inſpire them with; it is to no purpoſe, the Attempt is altogether vain: <hi>For it is a defenced City, an Iron Pillar, and Brazen Walls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Enemies of the Lord, and his People, may fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> they may poſſeſs the adjacent Countrey about it; they may prevent all Succors and Approaches for Relief; they may annoy them with continual Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries without; and reduce them to Extremities by Want, Famine, and incommodious Habitation within, yet they ſhall not prevail, all their Endeavours and Deſigns ſhall be fruſtrated, and render'd of no Effect.</p>
            <p>Let no Man entertain the leaſt umbrage of fear or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may; let no man deſpond or be perplexed with anxious Apprehenſions, tho' their Enemies proceed with Check
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36841:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->or Interruption; tho' their Friends and Allies may ſeem to neglect or forget them: yet they are ſecure from all inger and Surpriſe; their Force is irreſiſtible, and their Succeſs unqueſtionable; <hi>For the Lord is with them, and will deliver them.</hi> Nay, they may aſſuredly rely upon it; all the Powers of the Earth cannot hinder, or diſapoint it, <hi>For the Lord hath ſaid it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To apply this Text to the preſent Circumſtances in which we are.</p>
            <p>We have been ſurrounded in this poor City for divers Months; beleaguer'd by a multitude of mercileſs and implacable Enemies; expoſed to Danger, without ceaſing or intermiſſion: we have been deſerted by thoſe who came to our Relief; tempted by Parlies, and ſpecious Terms of Capitulation; undermined by treacherous Contrivances among our ſelves; exerciſed with all the varieties of Terror and Amazement; the ſmall Shot hath poured upon us like a ſhower of Hail; the great Guns, like Thunder, have ſhaken our Walls; and the Bombs, like Lightning, have ruin'd our Houſes; we have ſeen Death in all its horrible ſhapes, and we are every Moment entertain'd with ſpectacles of Miſery and Mortality; Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Diſeaſes are entered within our Gates; and pale Famine is viſible in very Countenance; the fond Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not a Morſel of Bread to appeaſe the languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cry of her ſtarved Infant: the grateful Son hath not wherewithal to ſuſtain his aged Parent: one Friend looks upon another, and ſees his Miſery, but cannot prevent a lingring Death; he that formerly had his Table cover'd with variety of Diſhes, knows not where to ſatisfie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with one wholeſom bit; we cannot refreſh our ſelves with ſuch Scraps and Morſels, as we formerly allow'd to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36841:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->our Dogs; nay, we are conſtrain'd to eat of ſuch thing as at another time humane nature would nauſeate and abhor. Nevertheleſs God has made us this day a defenced City, and an Iron Pillar, and Brazen Walls againſt the whole Land.</p>
            <p>He that was our King, and ſhould have treated u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like a nurſing Father, who ſolemnly promiſed, to defend the Eſtabliſhed Religion, and maintain us in our Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, has unnaturally bent his Forces to deſtroy us. He hath ſet up Idolatry in all corners of the Land; he hath animat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Natives to wreak their Malice and Revenge upo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us; he hath brought in the bloody <hi>French-men</hi> and Fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reigners to repeat thoſe Cruelties here, which with ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much Barbarity they have acted in our Neighbour-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Skene is added to the <hi>French</hi>-Bayonet; and the Rappeeres out-do the Dragoons. The Lords and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation, are as one Man combined againſt us; the Popiſh Prieſts, like the Bell-weathers of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Tumult, have led their Flocks, and involved their whole Nation in an unſatiable Thirſt after our Blood, and an implacable Reſolution to deſtroy us; ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friends round about us are plunder'd, driven from thei<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Habitations, and the whole Country is deſolate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated. Yet for all this, the Almighty God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and defended us, againſt the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Princes thereof, againſt the Prieſts thereof, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt the People of the Land.</p>
            <p>And tho hitherto (by the Mercy of God) we have been ſucceſsful in our Reſiſtance, and proſperous in our Sallies againſt them, yet they are inexorable in their Wrath, and reſtleſs in their malicious Deſigns; they mean to ſtorm us, or ſtarve us; they preſume upon their great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36841:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->Strength, and mighty Numbers; they flatter themſelves with an aſſurance, that we muſt one day fall into their hands; that one poor City cannot long reſiſt the united Forces of a whole Kingdom, and the auxiliary Aid of <hi>France.</hi> Therefore we are to expect the utmoſt Tryals, that their Hatred to our Religion and our Countrey can inflame and prompt them to. But let this be your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, tho' they ſhall fight againſt us, yet they ſhall not prevail againſt us.</p>
            <p>For the Lord is with us, the Lord is on our ſide, we will not fear what Man can do unto us. Let them truſt in Princes, and boaſt of their Horſes, but we will put our truſt in the Lord. Let them fall down before their Images, and vainly invoke the Angels and tutelar Saints; let them cry to the Holy Virgin to help them, and to St. <hi>Patrick</hi> to ſave them; We will make our Adreſſes to Him, who is only able to relieve us; our whole dependance ſhal be upon Him, who never faileth them that put their truſt in Him, who hath ſaid, <hi>He is with us, to deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, my Beloved, let me exhort you to be ſtedfaſt in your Duty; to be importunate with God in Prayers; to caſt your Care upon Him, with a lively Hope, and well-grounded Faith, to rouze up your wont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Courage; to arm your ſelves with your accuſtomed Reſolution; to fall upon the Enemies of God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Deſtroyers of your Eſtates and Country, the inhumane Murderers of your Friends and Brethren. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with a ſteady aſſurance of Succeſs and Victory, <hi>For the Ford is with you, and will deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
